<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An encouragement to colonies. By Sir William Alexander, knight..</title>
            <author>Stirling, William Alexander, Earl of, 1567 or 8-1640.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1625</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 106 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B00963</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 341A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S125341</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">56572762</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 56572762</idno>
            <idno type="VID">180885</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B00963)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 180885)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2143:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An encouragement to colonies. By Sir William Alexander, knight..</title>
                  <author>Stirling, William Alexander, Earl of, 1567 or 8-1640.</author>
                  <author>Stansby, William, fl. 1597-1638, printer.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 47 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Stansby.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1625..</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's mark (McK. 292) on t.p.; headpieces, initials.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-G⁴ (first leaf blank?).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Colonies --  History --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>America --  History --  1492-1763 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Canada --  History --  To 1760 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:180885:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN Encouragement TO COLONIES. By Sir WILLIAM ALEXANDER, KNIGHT.</p>
            <q>Alter erit tum Tiphis, &amp; altera quae vehat Argo delectos Heroas—</q>
            <figure>
               <head>FOR THOV SHALT LABOR PEACE PLENTIE</head>
               <figDesc>printer's device of William Stansby</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON Printed by <hi>William Stansby.</hi> 1625.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:180885:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:180885:2"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST EXCELLENT PRINCE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough you haue gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the Labours of ſome (as much admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for your courteſie as they for their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcretion) who might haue beene condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for preſuming to importune you for their Patron; yet it would ſeeme a prophanation of greatneſſe to place your name vpon the Fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſpice of euery vulgar Paper, but as no Worke hath more need of your countenance, then <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging of Colonies;</hi> So it would appeare to me (I know not ſuſpecting my owne partiali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, whither ſeduced by Deſire, or warranted by Reaſon) that there is no ground whereupon your
<pb facs="tcp:180885:3"/>countenance may ſhine with a more publike ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe. This is the way (making the Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt knowne in vnknowne parts) by ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying the neceſsities of many, with a lawfull in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of neceſſary commerce, to procure glorie vnto God, honour to your ſelfe, and benefit to the World; By this meanes, you that are borne to rule Nations, may bee the beginner of Nations, enlarging this Monarchie without bloud, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a Conqueſt without wronging of others, whereof in regard of your youth any good begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in this (like your vertue vpon which it doth depend) boding a ſpeedie Progreſſe Time in your own time, doth promiſe a great perfection. The glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of greatnes (that it may haue a harmonie with goodneſſe) conſiſting more in rayſing then in rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of others, it is a farre better courſe to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe fame by the Plantation of a new World, nor as many Princes haue done by the deſolation of this. And ſince your Royall Father during whoſe happie raigne, theſe ſeeds of Scepters haue beene firſt from hence ſowne in <hi>America,</hi> by his gracious fauour farre aboue any merit of mine hath emboldened mee the meaneſt of many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of his ſubiects to attempt ſo great an Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize, as to lay the foundation of a Worke that may ſo much import the good of that ancient
<pb facs="tcp:180885:3"/>Kingdome, where ſo many of your Anceſtors were buried, and where your ſelues were borne. I haue both by reading what doth reſt vpon Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, and by conferring with ſundry that haue beene imbarked in ſuch a buſineſſe, beene curious to remarke the managing thereof, that the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of times paſt might with the leſſe dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger at the charges of others, improoue them that are to practize at this preſent. And the fruits of my Labours I doe humbly offer heere vnto your Highneſſe, hoping by the commendable endeuours, therein remembred (though it ſelfe be but a tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiall Treatiſe, not worthy your ſight) to conci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liate your good opinion towards them that are to aduenture in this kind. Amongst whom (if euer my fortunes haue any conformitie with my mind) I purpoſe to contribute as much as my weake abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities can bee able to affoord for accompliſhing this braue Deſigne, wherein my greateſt Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhall be that both this Age and the Poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie may know how much I deſire by ſome obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble effect to be remembred for being</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Highneſſe moſt humble and affectionate Seruant. <hi>W. A.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:180885:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:180885:4"/>
            <head>AN ENCOVRAGEMENT TO COLONIES.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſending forth of Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies (ſeeming a nouelty) is eſteemed now to bee a ſtrange thing, as not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly being aboue the cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage of common men, but altogether alienated from their knowledge, which is no wonder, ſince that courſe though both ancient, and vſuall, hath beene by the intermiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſo many ages diſcontinued, yea was impoſsible to be practiſed ſo long as there was no vaſt ground, howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer men had beene willing, whereupon Plantations might haue beene made, yet there is none who will doubt but that the world in her infancy, and innocency, was firſt peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled after this manner.</p>
            <p>The next generations ſucceeding <hi>Shem</hi> planted in <hi>Aſia, Chams</hi> in <hi>Africke,</hi> and <hi>Iaphets</hi> in <hi>Europe: Abraham</hi> and <hi>Lot</hi> were Captaines of Colonies, the Land then being as free as the Seas are now, ſince they parted them in euery part where they paſſed, not taking notice of natiues with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:180885:5"/>impediment. That memorable troope of <hi>Iewes</hi> which <hi>Moſes</hi> led from <hi>Aegypt</hi> to <hi>Canaan</hi> was a kind of Colonie though miraculouſly conducted by God, who intended thereby to aduance his Church and to deſtroy the rejected Ethnikes. <hi>Salmanezer</hi> King of <hi>Aſhur</hi> was remarked for the firſt who did violate the naturall ingenuitie of this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable kind of policy by too politike an intention; for hauing tranſported the ten Tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to the end that tranſplanting and diſperſing them, hee might either wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken their ſtrength, or aboliſh their memorie by incorpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of them with his other Subjects; he to preuent the dangers incident amongſt remote vaſſals did ſend a Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie to inhabite <hi>Samaria</hi> of a purpoſe thereby to ſecure his late and queſtionable conqueſt.</p>
            <p>Who can imagine by this induſtrious courſe of Planta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, what an vnexpected progreſſe from a deſpiſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning hath beene ſuddenly made to the height of great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe! The <hi>Phoenicians</hi> quickly founded <hi>Sidon,</hi> and <hi>Tirus,</hi> ſo much renowned both by ſacred, and humane writers, and a few <hi>Tirians</hi> builded <hi>Carthage,</hi> which had firſt no more ground allowed her than could be compaſſed by the extended dimenſions of a Bulls hide, which for acquiring of the more ground they diuided in as many ſundrie parts as was poſsible, yet in end that Town became the Miſtreſſe of <hi>Afrike,</hi> and the riuall of <hi>Rome:</hi> and <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelfe that great Ladie of the World, and terrour to all Nations, am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitiouſly clayming for her firſt founders a few ſcandali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed fugitiues that fled from the ruines of <hi>Troy,</hi> did riſe from ſmall appearances to that exorbitancy of power, which at this day is remembred with admiration; Though the walls of it at that time were very lowe when the one bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did kill the other for jumping ouer them, either jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie already preuayling aboue naturall affection, or elſe vnaduiſed anger conſtructing that which might haue been caſually or careleſly done, in a ſiniſtrous ſenſe to the hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full behauiour of inſolency or ſcorne; Their number then was not only very ſmall, but they wanted women, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:180885:5"/>which they could not encreaſe, nor ſubſiſt, till they ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſhed the daughters of the <hi>Sabins,</hi> by a violent match at firſt, portending their future rapins, and what a furious off-ſpring they were likely to ingender. And when that haughty Citie beganne to ſuffer the miſeries which ſhe had ſo long beene accuſtomed to inflict vpon others, the vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Citie of <hi>Venice</hi> (keeping for ſo many ages a ſpotleſſe reputation) was firſt begunne by a few diſcouraged per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who fleeing from the furie of the barbarous Nations that then encroached vpon <hi>Italie,</hi> were diſtracted with feare and (ſeeking for their ſafety) did ſtumble vpon a commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious dwelling.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Graecians</hi> were the firſt, at leaſt of all the Gentiles, (who joyning learning with armes) did both doe, and write that which was worthie to be remembred; and that ſmall parcel of ground whoſe greatneſſe was then only va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lued by the vertue of the inhabitants, did plant <hi>Trapizonde</hi> in the Eaſt, and many other Cities in <hi>Aſia</hi> the leſſe, the protecting of whoſe liberties was the firſt cauſe of warre between them and the <hi>Perſian</hi> Monarchs; then beſides all the adjacent Iles they planted <hi>Siracuſa</hi> in <hi>Sicile,</hi> moſt part of <hi>Italie,</hi> which made it to bee called <hi>Graecia maior,</hi> and <hi>Marſeills</hi> in <hi>France.</hi> O what a ſtrange alteration! that this part, which did flouriſh thus, whileſt it was poſſeſſed by vigorous ſpirits, who were capable of great enterpriſes, did ſo many braue things ſhould now (the ſeate of baſe ſeruile people) become the moſt abject and contemptible part of all the Territories belonging to the barbarous <hi>Ottomans,</hi> whoſe inſolent Ianiſſaries (as the Pretorian Guards did with their Emperours, and Mamalukes of <hi>Egypt</hi> with their Soldans) preſume at this time to diſpoſe of the Regall power, vpbrayding the miſerable follie of Chriſtians, who dangerouſly embarqued in inteſtine warres, though inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by an encountring occaſion, neglect ſo great, ſo glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, and ſo eaſie a conqueſt.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Romanes</hi> comming to command a well peopled World, had no vſe of Colonies, but onely thereby to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:180885:6"/>ſuch old deſeruing Souldiers as (age and merit plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding an immunitie from any further conſtrained trauell) had brauely exceeded the ordinary courſe of time appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for military ſeruice, which cuſtome was vſed in <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, France, Spaine,</hi> and <hi>Brittaine,</hi> and likewiſe that the Townes erected in this ſort might ſerue for Citadels impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vpon euery conquered Prouince, whereof ſome doe flouriſh at this day, and of others nothing doth remaine but the very name onely, their ruines being ſo ruined, that wee can hardly condiſcend vpon what ſolitary part to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowe the fame of their former being.</p>
            <p>I am loth by diſputable opinions to dig vp the Tombes of them that more extenuated then the duſt are buried in obliuion &amp; will leaue theſe diſregarded relicts of greatneſſe to continue as they are, the ſcorne of pride, witneſsing the power of time. Neither will I after the common cuſtome of the world, ouerualuing things paſt diſualue the preſent, but conſidering ſeriouſly of that which is lately done in <hi>Ireland,</hi> doe finde a Plantation there inferiour to none that hath beene heretofore. The <hi>Babylonians</hi> hauing conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> did tranſplant them as expoſed to ruine in a remote Countrey, ſending others of their owne Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (that they might be vtterly extirpated) to inhabite <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria</hi> in their places. And our King hath only diuided the moſt ſeditious families of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> by diſperſing them in ſundry parts within the Countrey, not to extinguiſh, but to diſsipate their power, who now neither haue, nor giue cauſe of feare. The <hi>Romanes</hi> did build ſome Townes which they did plant with their owne people by all rigour to curbe the Natiues next adjacent thereunto, And our King hath incorporated ſome of his beſt <hi>Brittaines</hi> with the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> planted in ſundry places without power to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe, but onely to ciuilize them by their example. Thus <hi>Ireland</hi> which heretofore was ſcarcely diſcouered, and on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly irritated by others, prouing to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> as the <hi>Lowe-Countries</hi> did to <hi>Spaine,</hi> a meanes whereby to waſte their men, and their money, is now really conquered, becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:180885:6"/>a ſtrength to the State, and a glorie to his Majeſties gouernment, who hath in the ſetling thereof excelled all that was commended in any ancient Colonie.</p>
            <p>As all firſt were encouraged to Plantations by the large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the conqueſts that were propoſed vnto them, fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring onely want of people, and not of land, ſo in after ages when all knowne parts became peopled, they were quickly entangled with the other extremitie, grudging to be boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded within their proſpect, and jarring with their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours for ſmall parcels of ground, a ſtrife for limits limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the liues of many who entring firſt in controuerſie vpon a point of profit though with the loſſe of ten times more, valuing their honour by the opinion of others be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hooued to proceed as engaged for the ſafety of their repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. Then richeſſe being acquired by induſtrie, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie by employments, theſe two did beget auarice, and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, which lodging in ſome ſubtile heads vpon a poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike conſideration to vnite inteſtine diuiſions did transferre their ſplene to forraine parts, not ſeeking to rectifie the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, but to buſie them abroad where leaſt harme was feared, and moſt benefit expected, ſo that where they had firſt in a peaceable ſort ſought for Lands onely wherewith to furniſh their neceſsity, which conueniency, or ſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, did eaſily accommodate, now ayming at greatneſſe the deſires of men growne infinite, made them ſtrangers to contentment, and enemies to reſt.</p>
            <p>Some Nations ſeeking to exchange for better ſeates, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to command their neighbours, there was for many ages no ſpeach but of wrongs and reuenges, conqueſts and reuolts, razings and ruining of States, a continuall reuolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion determining the periods of Time by the miſeries of mankind, and in regard of the populouſneſſe of theſe ages during the Monarchies of the <hi>Aſſirians, Perſians, Graecians,</hi> and <hi>Romanes,</hi> the world could not haue ſubſiſted if it had not beene purged of turbulent humours by letting out the bloud of many thouſands, ſo that warre was the vniuerſall Chirurgeon of theſe diſtempered times: And thereafter
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:180885:7"/>O what monſtrous multitudes of people were ſlaine by huge deluges of barbarous armies that ouerflowed <hi>Italie, France</hi> and <hi>Spaine!</hi> and the Chriſtians haue long beene ſubject to the like calamities wanting a commoditie how they might (not wronging others) in a Chriſtian manner employ the people that were more chargeable then neceſſary at home, which was the cauſe of much miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe among themſelues, till at that time when <hi>Spaine</hi> was ſtriuing with <hi>France</hi> how to part <hi>Italie,</hi> as <hi>Italie</hi> had formerly done with <hi>Carthage</hi> how to part <hi>Spaine.</hi> Then it pleaſed God hauing pitie of the Chriſtians who for pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes of ſmall importance did prodigally proſtitute the liues of them whom hee had purchaſed with ſo pretious a ranſome, as it were for diuerting that violent kind of vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, to diſcouer a new world, which it would ſeeme in all reaſon ſhould haue tranſported them with deſignes of more moment, whereby glory and profit with a guiltleſſe labour was to bee attayned with leſſe danger whereunto they are as it were inuited, and prouoked with ſo many e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent aduantages palpably expoſed to any cleare judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that I thinke (this obuious facilitie vilifying that which a further difficulty might the more endeare) the eaſineſſe of the prey hath blunted the appetite.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Chriſtopher Columbus</hi> had in vaine propounded this enterpriſe to diuers Chriſtian Princes, <hi>Iſabella</hi> of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtile</hi> againſt the opinion of her husband (though ſo much renowned for wit yet not reaching this myſterie) did firſt furniſh him for a Voyage, as if it were fatall that that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhould owe the greateſt part of their greatneſſe to the female Sexe, And if the <hi>Spaniards</hi> would ſincerely, and gratefully haue beſtowed the benefits whereby God did al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lure them to poſſeſſe this Land for the planting of it with Chriſtians enclined to ciuilitie, and religion, it had at this day conſidering the excellency of the ſoyle, for all the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections that nature could affoord; beene the moſt ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly accompliſhed place of the world, but it hath infortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natly fallen out farre otherwiſe, that the treaſures that are
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:180885:7"/>drawne from thence (mynes to blowe vp mindes and rockes to ruine faith) doe proue the ſeed of diſſention, the ſinewes of the warre, and nurcerie of all the troubles a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Spaniards</hi> that were ſo happie as to chance firſt vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this new World, were of all others (hauing but a vaſt mountainous Countrey) in regard of their ſcarcity of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, moſt vnfit for planting thereof, and could not but ſoone haue abandoned the ſame, if they had not ſo quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly encountred with the rich Mynes of <hi>Mexico, New Spaine</hi> and <hi>Peru,</hi> which were once likely to haue beene loſt for lacke of wood, till the way was inuented of refining Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer by quickſiluer, which may bee eaſily done out of any oare that is free from Lead, and (all the <hi>Spaniards</hi> diſday<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning worke as a ſeruile thing belowe their abilities) their greateſt trouble is the want of workmen: for the Natiues that are extant, ſuruiuing many vexations, if they become ciuile out of an indulgency to libertie, and eaſe, whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all the <hi>Americans</hi> (liking better of a penurious life thus then to haue plenty with taking paines) are naturally encli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that they may haue a ſecure eaſe warranted by an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, doe betake themſelues to Cloiſters, ſo that they haue no meanes to proſecute theſe workes but by drawing yeer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a great number of <hi>Negroes</hi> from <hi>Angola,</hi> and other parts, which being but an vnnaturall merchandiſe, are bought at a deare rate, and maintayned with danger, for they once of late, as I haue heard from one that was there at that time deſigned to murther their Maſters, by a plot which ſhould haue beene put in execution vpon a Good-friday, when all being exerciſed at their deuotion were leaſt apt to apprehend ſuch a wicked courſe, and it is alwaies feared that to reuenge what of neceſsitie they muſt ſuffer, and to procure their libertie hating moſt what they feele for the preſent, and hoping for better by a change, they will joyne with any ſtrong enemy that landing there dare attempt the conqueſt of that Countrey.</p>
            <p>I will not here inſiſt in ſetting downe the manner how
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:180885:8"/>the <hi>Spaniards</hi> made themſelues Maſters of ſo many rich and pleaſant Countries, but doe leaue that to their owne Hiſtories, though I confeſſe (like wiſemen) they are very ſparing to report the eſtate of theſe parts, and doe barre all ſtrangers from hauing acceſſe thereunto, wiſhing to enjoy that which they loue in priuate, and not inconſiderately vanting by the vanitie of praiſes to procure vnto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues the vexation that they might ſuffer by the earneſt purſuit of emulating riuals, but as they did brauely begin, and reſolutely proſecute their Diſcoueries in <hi>America,</hi> ſo hath it juſtly recompenced their courage, prouing the ground of all that greatneſſe which at this time (not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe) doth make them (as able, or willing, to conquer others if not both) ſo much ſuſpected by euery jealous State. And <hi>Henry</hi> the Seuenth the <hi>Salomon</hi> of <hi>England</hi> had his judgement onely condemned for neglecting that good occaſion which was firſt offered vnto him by <hi>Colum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus,</hi> yet did he preſently ſeeke to repaire his errour by ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding forth <hi>Sebaſtian Chabot</hi> a <hi>Venetian</hi> who did diſcouer the Ile of <hi>Newfound-land,</hi> and this part of the Continent of <hi>America</hi> now intended to bee planted by his Majeſties Subjects vnder the name of New <hi>England,</hi> and New <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> ſo that the fruits of his happie raigne ſtill growing to a greater perfection and now ripe to bee gathered by this age, as he made way by the marriage of his eldeſt daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for vniting theſe two Nations at home, ſo did hee the ſame likewiſe by this diſcouerie abroad, but the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of both was reſerued for his Majeſtie now raign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and no Prince in the world may more eaſily effectuate ſuch a purpoſe ſince his Dominions affoord abundance of braue men ſingularly valued for able bodies and actiue ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits whereof the <hi>Engliſh</hi> haue already giuen good proofe of their ſufficiency in forraine Plantations; but before I proceed further in that which doth concerne them I muſt obſerue what the <hi>French</hi> haue done in this kind.</p>
            <p>All ſuch aduentrous deſignes out of ignorance, or enuie (either contemned, or doubtfully ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſured) are neuer appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:180885:8"/>nor imitated, til they be juſtified by the ſucceſſe, &amp; then many who had firſt been too diſtruſtfull falling in the other extremitie of an implicite confidence, to redeeme their former neglects, doe precipitate themſelues in needleſſe dangers. After that the <hi>Spaniards</hi> were knowne to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper, and that it was conceiued by the Voyage of <hi>Chabot</hi> what a large vaſtneſſe this new Continent was likely to proue, <hi>Francis</hi> the firſt did furniſh forth <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ohn Verrizzon</hi> a <hi>Florentine,</hi> who did diſcouer that part of <hi>America</hi> which was firſt (and moſt juſtly) called <hi>New France,</hi> and now <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra Florida.</hi> And vpon his returne he affirming it to be (as it is indeed for all the excellencies of nature) one of the moſt pleaſant parts of the world, This was the cauſe that after a long delay (during the ſpace of two Princes whole raignes) ſome new Diſcoueries reuiuing the memory of this, in the yeere of God 1562. <hi>Charles</hi> the ninth (hauing a haughty mind, and being ſo rauiſhed with a deſire of glorie, that he was ſometimes tempted by ſiniſtrous ſuggeſtions in ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king after it to goe vpon wrong grounds) was quickly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amoured with the eminency of ſuch a ſingular deſigne, wherein hee did employ <hi>Iohn Ribaut,</hi> who comming to <hi>Florida,</hi> was kindly receiued by the Natiues there, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing made choice of a place where to build a Fort, after hee had ſtayed a time giuing direction for ſuch things as were neceſſarie to be done, he left forty men therein when hee came away with one Captaine <hi>Albert</hi> to command them, who after that hee had with difficulty beene freed from the danger of famine, and of fire (vnſeaſonably affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting the diſuſed auſteritie of the Ancients) did for a ſmall offence hang one of his companie with his owne hands, ſo loſing both the dignitie of his place, and the hearts of his people at one time, which hee ſhould haue beene extremely ſtudious to preſerue, eſteeming them as fellowes of his ſufferings, and coheires of his hopes, at leaſt the qualitie of the offence and neceſsitie of his death ſhould haue beene made ſo cleare, that as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting a common good, all (if not vrging it) ſhould at
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:180885:9"/>leaſt haue condiſcended thereunto, but this errour of his was acquited in as rude a manner: for his companie put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him to death did make choice of another Captaine, and deſpairing of a new ſupplie though wanting skilfull workmen for ſuch a purpoſe (neceſsitie ſharpning their wits) they builded a little Barque which they calfatted and made fit for the Seas with the Gummes of trees which they found there in ſtead of Pitch, and in place of Sayles they furniſhed her with ſuch linnens as they had vpon their beds, and being thus ſet forth (couragiouſly ouercomming a number of admirable difficulties) did returne to <hi>France</hi> after a deſperate manner.</p>
            <p>The dangerleſſe returne, and plauſible hopes of <hi>Ribaut,</hi> aſsiſted by the ſerious perſwaſions of the Admirall, (the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued opinion of whoſe not queſtioned wiſedome was enough to warrant any thing that had his approbation) did moue the <hi>French</hi> King to ſend out a great number of men with a competent prouiſion of all things requiſite vnder the charge of Monſieur <hi>Laudonier,</hi> who had a proſperous Voyage, and a congratulated arriuall at the <hi>French</hi> Fort by the Sauages in <hi>Florida,</hi> but immediatly thereafter hee was extremely perplexed with the vnexpected, mutinies and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctious offers of ſome whom he had carried with him, who had not gone thither intending what they pretended, out of a cleare reſolution to inhabite that bounds, but did one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly flee from ſome inconueniences that had vexed them at home, ſuch men as hating labour they could not induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly ſerue by their endeauours in a mechanike trade, ſo were they not capable of generous inſpirations that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke magnanimitie, but habitually bred to vice were natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally enemies to vertue, which made thirtie of them taking away a Barke that belonged to the Plantation betake them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to the Seas in hope (continuing as they had beene accuſtomed in naughty courſes) to ſeize vpon a prize whereby they might incontinent bee made rich; and their deſigne in ſome meaſure had the projected iſſue, but in place of raiſing their fortunes (the Lord neuer bleſsing
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:180885:9"/>them that abandon ſuch a worthie worke, much leſſe with a minde to doe miſchiefe) it proued in end away to worke their confuſion, And <hi>Laudoniere</hi> being hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie to haue his companie purged of ſuch peſtiferous fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes did carrie himſelfe brauely as became a commander, aduiſedly enquiring concerning the Sauages, what their force was, what relation they had one to another, where they were friends or foes, how their pleaſures were placed, and by what accounts they reckoned their gaines or loſſes, ſo that hee was alwaies ready as might ſtand beſt with the good of his affaires to aſsiſt, or oppoſe, to diuide, or agree any partie, thus by ſhewing power purchaſing authoritie, til he drew the ballance of all buſineſſe to bee ſwayed where hee would as being Maſter of the Countrey. Hereupon (the vmbragious aſperſions of enuie ſo darkening reaſon that it could not diſcerne merite at leaſt out of a depraued opinion with a derogatory cenſure cancelling all naturall ingenuitie, could not or would not acknowledge what was due thereunto) a report was ſpread in <hi>France</hi> by ſome that <hi>Laudoniere</hi> liued like a Prince diſdayning the condition of a Subject, and the <hi>French</hi> out of a prepoſterous policie fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring what they ſhould haue wiſhed that one of their owne Nation could be too great abroad, they ſent backe <hi>Ribaut</hi> with a new commiſsion to ſucceed him in his charge, (ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king thereby the firſt foundation of a growing greatneſſe) who ſeeking to ſteale priuately vpon him to preuent aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſements that hee might take him at vnawares did hardly eſcape to haue beene ſunke at his firſt entrie.</p>
            <p>Immediatly after that <hi>Ribaut</hi> was admitted Gouernour (<hi>Laudoniere</hi> hauing ſhewed himſelfe as dutifull to obey as he had beene skilfull in commanding) intelligence was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen them that ſixe <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Ships were riding at an anchor not farre from thence, and he ambitiouſly aſpiring to grace his beginning with ſome great matter againſt the aduice of all the reſt with an obſtinate reſolution would needs goe and purſue them taking the beſt of the companie with him, and ſo left the Fort weakely guarded, which made it
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:180885:10"/>to proue an eaſie prey for the <hi>Spaniards</hi> of whom the moſt part leauing their Ships (a minde tranſported with hope not thinking of paine) did march thorow the woods whence no perill was expected, and in a maruellous ſtormy night, as if the very Heauens (acceſſarily culpable) had conſpired with the malice of men for the working of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief. When the <hi>Frenchmen</hi> (too much affecting their owne eaſe) had neglected their watch, ſurprizing their Fort did put them all to the ſword, which extreme crueltie of theirs was brauely reuenged by one Captaine <hi>Gorgues</hi> a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of <hi>Burdeaux,</hi> who out of a generous diſpoſition being ſenſible of this publike injurie whereby all his Nation was intereſted, as if it had only in particular imported the ruine of his owne fortunes, went of purpoſe to this part, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly before his comming was knowne contracting a great friendſhip with the Sauages who did hate the auſtere coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, and rigorous gouernment of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> when it came to be compared with the inſinuating formes of the <hi>French,</hi> he found the meanes by a ſtratagem that he vſed to entrap the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> by the death of them all expiating that which they had made his Countreymen formerly to ſuffer, yet after the manner of many being more apt to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire then to preſerue (acting greater things when carried with the impetuoſitie of a preſent fury then hee could confirme with the conſtant progreſſe of a well ſetled reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution) he made no more vſe of his victorie, but returned back to <hi>France,</hi> flattering himſelf with the hope of a trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phall welcome, in place whereof by ſome meanes made Court he was proclaimed a Rebell, as a ſacrifice appointed to appeaſe <hi>Spaine.</hi> This was the laſt thing that the <hi>French</hi> did in <hi>Florida.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next forraine aduenture was likewiſe procured by the Admirall, a worthie man, who would gladly haue di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed the vindictiue diſpoſitions of his Countrymen from the bloudy ciuile warres wherewith they were then entan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled, to proſecute ſome braue enterpriſe abroad whereby they might not be made guilty, and yet haue glorie, The
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:180885:10"/>man that did offer himſelfe for Conductor of the Voyage was one <hi>Villegagnon</hi> a Knight of <hi>Malta</hi> who then prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to be of the reformed religion (as all doe who affect to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare what they are not indeed) making ſhew of extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary remorſe, and zeale, and that hee had a deſire to retire himſelfe from the vanitie, corruption, and vexation of their parts to ſome remote place in <hi>America,</hi> where profeſsing himſelfe ſuch as he was, he might (free from all kind of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediments) begin a new life, and where he hoped to found ſuch a Colony as ſhould ſerue for a retreat to all thoſe of the reformed Religion who (weary of the perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s at home) would goe where they might liue with ſafety, and enjoy the libertie of their conſcience, by this meanes hee got a great number to acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany him, amongſt whom was <hi>Iohn de Lerie</hi> their Miniſter, a learned man who wrote a diſcourſe of all that paſſed in this Voyage, and there were ſundry others that came from the Towne of <hi>Geneua,</hi> ſo that hauing a reaſonable number and well prouided, hee embarqued and ſayled towards <hi>Braſile,</hi> making choice of a place fit for a Plantation, where they found (the ſoile excellent, the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues well inclined towards them, and a ſupplie comming in due time) all things ſo concurring for their contentment that they might haue begunne a great worke happie and hopefull for their poſteritie, if <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>illagagnon</hi> had beene the man that he made them beleeue he was, but he apparantly neuer louing them of the Religion in his heart had coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeited to doe ſo for a time, onely (angling their affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions) by this meanes to draw a ſupply from them; for as ſoone as hee was ſetled in his gouernment, that hee found himſelfe ſtrong enough by Catholikes, and others of his friends that he had with him to doe (as hee thought) what he would, ſtraight, remouing the maske that hypocriſie had put vpon him, he diſcharged all exerciſe of the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med religion which no man with more feruency had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed then himſelfe, commanding all to conforme them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to the orders that he had ſet downe, but (in place of feare which he purpoſed to giue, receiuing hut contempt)
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:180885:11"/>this baſe kind of carriage did quite ouerthrow and they making a partie amongſt themſelues did remoue with their Miniſter <hi>Iohn de Lerie,</hi> which diuiſion of their Colonie in two was the was cauſe that neither could ſubſiſt, ſo that <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>illagagnon</hi> abandoning that Countrey, all after many ſeuerall deſignes returned vnto <hi>France,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing found no impediment to ſo good a purpoſe but the peruerſeneſſe of ſuch mindes as they had earried with them.</p>
            <p>Monſieur <hi>De Larauerdier</hi> a very worthie Gentleman did of late enterpriſe the like courſe in the ſame bounds, and was croſſed in the ſame manner by the difference of Religion (diſputations quickning them to contrauert who will not be conuerted) that diſtracted his companie with ſeuerall opinions, yet at this time a long continuance ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king that leſſe ſtrange amongſt the <hi>French</hi> then it was wont to be, the Gentleman did command with ſuch judgement, and diſcretion, that what euer priuate diſlike was, it neuer burſted forth in any open inſurrection. And for the ſpace of foure or fiue yeeres being befriended by the Natiues, though continually oppoſed both by the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and by the <hi>Portugals,</hi> yet he alwaies preuayled, liuing (as himſelfe told me) with more contentment then euer he had done in his time either before or ſince; hee could neuer diſcerne any Winter there by the effects, ſeeing no ſtormy weather at all, and finding a continuall greenneſſe to beautifie the fields, which did affoord ſuch abundance, and variety of all things neceſſary for the maintaynance, that they were neuer in any danger of famine, but in end finding no more people comming from <hi>France,</hi> and fearing that time ſhould weare away them that were with him; then being flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the loue of his natiue ſoyle, longing to ſee his friends, and tempted by the hope of a preſent gaine, which as he imagined might the better enable him for ſome ſuch purpoſe in an other part, he capitulated with the <hi>Spaniards</hi> to ſurre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der the place hauing aſſura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce giuen him for a great ſumme of money which ſhould haue beene deliuered in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:180885:11"/>
               <hi>Spaine,</hi> but comming to receiue the ſame (it being more eaſie to pay debt by reuenging a pretended injurie then with money which ſome would rather keepe then their Faith) he was caſt in priſon, where hee remayned long, till at laſt he was deliuered by the mediation of our Kings Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour, and came here where I ſpake with him of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to giue his Majeſtie thankes- I heare that for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent he is now at <hi>Rochell</hi> (with a hope to repaire his error) ready to embarque for ſome ſuch like enterpriſe. This is all that the <hi>Frenchmen</hi> haue done in the South parts of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merica,</hi> and now I will make mention of their proceedings in theſe parts that are next vnto vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Francis</hi> the firſt of <hi>France</hi> a braue Prince, and natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly giuen to great things, after the Voyage made by <hi>Iohn Verrizan</hi> (<hi>Chabot</hi> hauing diſcouered the Continent for <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeuenth) did ſend forth <hi>Iames Quartier</hi> one of Saint <hi>Malo,</hi> who by two ſeuerall Voyages did diſcouer the Riuer of <hi>Cannada,</hi> and by his relation doth commend it exceedingly as being fertile in variety of Fiſhes, and bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered with many pleaſant meadowes, and ſtately woods, hauing in ſundry parts abundance of Vines growing wilde, chiefly in one Ile which he hath called by the name of the Ile of <hi>Orleans.</hi> This man neuer made any Plantation at all, but onely diſcouered and traffiqued with the Sauages, neither was there any further done by <hi>Roberwall,</hi> who did liue one Winter at Cape <hi>Breton.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Marqueſſe <hi>De la Roche</hi> by a Commiſsion from <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth, intending a Voyage for <hi>Cannada,</hi> hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened by the way vpon the Ile of <hi>Sablon</hi> (which is now comprehended within the Patent of <hi>New Scotland</hi>) and there (truſting to the ſtrength of the place where there are no Sauages at all) landed ſome of his men till hee ſhould haue found a conuenient place within the maine Land fit for habitation, promiſing then to returne for them; but it was his fortune by reaſon of contrary winds neuer to finde the maine Land, being blowne backe to <hi>France</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſeeing of them, where he was in the time of the ciuile
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:180885:12"/>warres (ſuch is the vncertainty of worldly things produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing vnexpected effects) taken priſoner by the Duke of <hi>Mercoeur,</hi> and ſhortly after died, ſo that his people whom hee had left at <hi>Sablon</hi> furniſhed but for a ſhort time had quickly ſpent their prouiſions, and tooke for their maintay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance onely ſuch things as the place it ſelfe did without labour freely affoord, which hath a race of Kowes (as is thought) firſt tranſported thither by the <hi>Portugals</hi> that haue long continued there, and ſundry roots fit to be eaten, with abundance of Fiſhes, Fowle and Veniſon. And (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing no meanes to liue but by ſport) as for their apparell they clothed themſelues with the skinnes of ſuch crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures as they could kill by Land, or Sea, ſo that liuing there for the ſpace of twelue yeeres when they were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth who had hired a Fiſherman to bring them home, as I haue heard from them that did ſee them at firſt before the King, they were in very good health, and looked as well, as if they had liued all that time in <hi>France:</hi> But hauing beene abuſed by the Fiſherman who (cunningly concealing that he had beene directed by the King) did bargaine with them to haue all their skinnes for tranſporting them home, which were of great value, ſome of them being of blacke Foxes, which were ſold at fiftie pounds ſterling a piece, and aboue, for the recouerie thereof they intended a proceſſe againſt him before the Court of Parliament at <hi>Paris,</hi> wherein by the equitie of their cauſe, or by the compaſsion of the Iudges, they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayled, gayning by that meanes a ſtocke wherewith to traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique in theſe parts againe.</p>
            <p>Monſieur <hi>De Montes</hi> procuring a Patent from <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth of <hi>Cannada</hi> from the 40. degree Eaſtward compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending all the bounds that is now both within <hi>New Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>New Scotland</hi> (after that Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> had formerly giuen one thereof as belonging to this Crowne by <hi>Chabots</hi> Diſcouerie) did ſet forth with a hundred per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons fitted for a Plantation, carried in two ſhips of ſmall burthen, which parting from <hi>France</hi> on ſeuerall dayes did
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:180885:12"/>appoint their meeting at the Port of <hi>Campſeau,</hi> but the ſhip wherein Monſieur <hi>De Montes</hi> had placed himſelfe going firſt, and fearing the huge Mountaines of Ice that diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing from the farre Northerne parts come alongſt the coaſt of <hi>Newfound-land</hi> during the Spring time, did take her courſe more to the South, and arriued at Port <hi>De Muton</hi> a Bay now in the fore-land of <hi>New Scotland,</hi> from whence one of the Natiues of the Countrey (either out of courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, or to gayne a reward) leauing his Wife and Children (as a pledge, or elſe to bee nouriſhed with them) went to <hi>Campſeau,</hi> and within a weeke brought them newes from their other Ship that had arriued there, which comming to them, and Monſieur <hi>Champlein</hi> who had gone in a ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lop to diſcouer the coaſt being returned, they ſayled toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Weſtwards to Cape <hi>Sable,</hi> and from thence North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to Bay Saint <hi>Maries,</hi> where towards the South ſide thereof they found good meadowes and arable ground fit to be planted vpon, and towards the North a mountai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous and minerall bounds, hauing diſcouered one veine of metall that did hold Siluer, and two of Iron ſtone: After this, hauing ſeene Port <hi>Royall,</hi> they went to the Riuer cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by them <hi>Sante Croix,</hi> but more fit now to bee called <hi>Tweed,</hi> becauſe it doth diuide <hi>New England</hi> and <hi>New Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> bounding the one of them vpon the Eaſt, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vpon the Weſt ſide thereof, here they made choice of an Ile that is within the middle of the ſame where to win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, building houſes ſufficient to lodge their number; There, beſides other ſorts of wood, they had ſtore of Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dar trees, and found the ground very fertile as it did proue afterwards, bringing forth that which they did ſow with an extraordinary encreaſe, yet during the Winter time when they could not conueniently goe to the maine Land, they found it a very incommodious dwelling, ſpecially for want of freſh Springs; And the ſoyle being of it ſelfe humid, and obnoxious to waters, they had not beene ſo induſtrious as to caſt a ditch wherewith to drie the ground whereupon their houſes ſtood, and in end finding that a little Ile was
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:180885:13"/>but a kind of large priſon, they reſolued to returne vnto Port <hi>Royall,</hi> whereof I will giue a particular Deſcription, becauſe it was the place of their reſidence, as I intend it to be for the chiefe Colonie of the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Nation, grounding that which I am to deliuer vpon ſuch Diſcourſes as the <hi>Frenchmen</hi> haue written, and vpon that which I haue heard reported by ſundry others who haue ſeene the ſame.</p>
            <p>The entry in Port <hi>Royall</hi> is from the South ſide of a great Bay, which doth make the South part of <hi>New Scotland</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt an Ile, and hath the paſſage at firſt ſo narrow, with a current ſo violent, that Ships can hardly enter if they take not the Tide right, and may eaſily be commanded by any Ordnance that is planted on either ſide, where there are parts fit for that purpoſe; As ſoone as they are within the Bay, it doth enlarge it ſelfe to the bredth of ſeuen or eight miles, and doth continue ſo as if it were ſquare for the like bounds in length; There are within the ſame two Iles e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one of them extending it ſelfe about three miles in circuit, and both are well garniſhed with trees, and graſſe; Diuers Riuers and Brookes doe fall within this large bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome on euery ſide, of which the chiefe is one that doth come from the South, being diſcouered to be aboue fortie miles portatiue, and it hath all alongſt on euery ſide for the bounds of a mile, or halfe a mile at leaſt, very faire mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes which are ſubject to bee ouerflowed at high tides, and there is Land fit to be laboured lying betweene them and the woods, which doe compaſſe all about with very faire trees of ſundry ſorts, as Oakes, Aſh, Playnes, Maple, Beech, Birch, Cypreſſe, Pine and Firre; The great Riuer doth abound exceedingly in Salmon and Smelts during their ſeaſon, and euery little Brooke in Trouts. One Lake within this Bay hath yeerely a great quantitie of Herrings, which by reaſon of a ſtrict way which they paſſe are eaſie to be taken, and all the yeere ouer they neuer want ſhell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſh, ſuch as Lobſters, Crabs, Cockles and Muſſels. The chiefe beaſts that inhabite the Woods there, are Ellans, Hart, Hind, and fallow Deere, with ſtore of other wilde
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:180885:13"/>beaſts, ſuch as Wolues, Beares, Foxes, and Otters, but the moſt vſefull of all is the Beauer, both for his fleſh that is eſteemed to be very delicate for eating, and for the skinne that is of good value; as for wild foule, there is great varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and ſtore, of Partridges, Plouers, Woodcockes, Larkes, Wild Geeſe, Wild Duckes, Heron and Crane, with many other forts peculiar to that part of the World, and not knowne here.</p>
            <p>Vpon the Eaſt ſide of this Port the <hi>French</hi> did entrench themſelues, building ſuch houſes as might ſerue to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modate their number, and a little from thence <hi>Monſieur Champlein</hi> did cut a walke through the Woods, where they delighted to repaire in Summer to ſhroud themſelues from the heate, and the rather that they had a ſweet Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lodie which was made by the varietie of voyces, of ſinging Birds which without any affectation did affoord them na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall Muſicke.</p>
            <p>Some ſixe miles further vp that ſide of the Riuer they built a Barne, and laboured ground for Wheat; ouer againſt which they made-a Water-mill vpon a Riuer, that doth fall in on the Weſt ſide, the Damme of it beeing there where the Herrings haunt moſt, and they did likewiſe try ſome ground neere by for Wheate, whereas their owne Writers make mention, they reaped aboue fortie for one, but what they did was rather trying the nature of the ſoile to ſatisfie their curioſitie then to haue a quantitie fit for their maintenance, which they truſted to bee ſent vnto them by two Merchants from the <hi>Rochell,</hi> and were that way well furniſhed ſo long as they keeped their skinnes to giue them in exchange (but the Merchants either by ſome priuate conueyances) or by the comming in of ſome <hi>Flemmings</hi> to traffique, being diſappointed by the Planters as ſoone as they miſſed their preſent Commoditie did like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe fruſtrate them of the prouiſions that they expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted. Whereupon <hi>Monſieur de Montes</hi> betaking him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to trade for Furres. <hi>Monſieur Poutrincourt</hi> reſolued to proſecute the Plantation at that place, and lent for his So<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:180885:14"/>
               <hi>Biencourt</hi> to <hi>France,</hi> to bargaine with ſome that would ſend them a ſupply, ſuch as was requiſite for eſtabliſhing of that Colony.</p>
            <p>The firſt that embraced his Propoſitions were the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites who as they haue ordinarly good wits which made them the rather capable of ſo aduantagious a proiect, ſo they were the more animated thereunto (by vpbrayding the lazineſſe of our Clergie) to ſhew with what feruencie they trauell to propagate the Goſpell in doing whereof (whither it be ambition or deuotion that prouokes them ſparing no paines) they haue trauelled both to the Eaſt and Weſt <hi>Indies,</hi> and to that admired Kingdome of <hi>China;</hi> their Societie in <hi>France</hi> preuayling with all that had any incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation either to religion, or to vertue did eaſily gather a voluntary contribution for the furthering of ſo commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable a purpoſe, thereafter they ſent away two Fathers of their company with a new ſupply of all things neceſſarie to the Plantation at Port <hi>Royall,</hi> but ſhortly after their ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riuall (their predominant diſpoſition hardly yeelding to any Superiour, ſpecially if it be a Secular power) they be-beganne to contradict <hi>Poutrincourt,</hi> in the execution of theſe Decrees which had beene giuen forth by him as Ciuil Magiſtrate of that place. Whereupon the Gentleman ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamely diſcontented, and wearie of conteſting with them, hauing ſaid that it was his part to rule them vpon earth, and theirs onely to guide him the way to Heauen, he returned backe to <hi>France,</hi> leauing his Sonne <hi>Biencourt</hi> in his place, who being a youth at that time of more courage then circumſpectneſſe, diſdayning to be controlled by them whom he had inuited thither, and ſcorning their inſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table preſumption, and imperious kinde of carriage, vſing Spirituall Armes for Temporall ends, whoſe ſpleene had excommunicated and branded him with a Spirituall cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, hee threatned them by his Temporall power with a more palpable paniſhment, ſo that after much controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, reſoluing to ſeparate themſelues, the two Ieſuites ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a part of the company with them, went from thence
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:180885:14"/>to a place in <hi>New England,</hi> called by them Mount <hi>Deſert'</hi> where they ſeated themſelues, and hauing a ſupply from the Queene Mother, did plant ſundry fruit trees of the moſt delicate kinds in <hi>France,</hi> ſuch as Apricockes and Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches neuer intending to remoue from thence.</p>
            <p>At this time Sir <hi>Samuell Argall,</hi> who hath beene Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour of <hi>Virginia,</hi> coaſting alongſt <hi>New England,</hi> to traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique, diſcouer, or to acquire things neceſſary for the Sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therne Colonie in theſe parts, where the Lands are reputed to be more fertile, and the Seas more frequented, did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue by a deſcription made vnto him by the Sauages, that there were ſome come from this part of the World to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habit there, and being iealous of any thing that might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogate from the honour, or prooue preiudiciall to the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of his Nation, whereof their intereſt in this was eaſie to be apprehended, hee went whereas hee was informed that they were, and his vnexpected arriuall, as it would ſeeme, not onely amazing the mindes of the <hi>French,</hi> but likewiſe preuenting their preparation, and reſolution, he approched ſo neere to a ſhip that lay before their Fore, that hee beate them all that were within, with Musket ſhot, from ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king any vſe of their Ordnance, and killed one of the two Ieſuites, who was giuing fire to a Peece; hauing taken the ſhip he landed and went before the Fort, ſummoning them that were within to yeeld themſelues, who at the firſt made ſome difficultie, asking a time to aduiſe, but that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing refuſed, they priuately abandoned the Fort, ſtealing out by ſome back way into the Woods, where they ſtayed one night, and the next day comming backe rendred them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, giuing vp the Patent they had from the <hi>French</hi> King to bee cancelled, hee vſed them courteouſly, as their owne Writers doe make mention, ſuffering ſuch as had a minde to goe for <hi>France,</hi> to ſeeke out fiſhers ſhips wherein they might bee tranſported, the reſt that were willing to goe for <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irginia,</hi> went thither alongſt with him, no man hauing loſt his life, but onely that one Ieſuite who was kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led whileſt they made reſiſtance during the time of the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:180885:15"/>conflict, thereafter Father <hi>Biard</hi> the other of the Ieſuites comming back from <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irginia,</hi> with Sir <hi>Samuell Argall,</hi> out of the indigeſtable malice that he had conceiued againſt <hi>Biencourt,</hi> did informe him where he had planted himſelfe offering (as hee did) to conduct him thither. As ſoone as they were entred within the Port, neere the vppermoſt of the Ilands, Sir <hi>Samuell</hi> directing the ſhip to ride at a reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable diſtance to attend occaſions before the Fort, did land himſelfe with fortie of the beſt of his men vpon a Medow, where immediatly they heard a Peece of Ordnance from the Fort, and he conceiuing ſince it was ſhot whilſt it could do no harme that it was done either but to giue terrour to them, or to warne ſome that might happen to bee abroad, Did make the greater haſte towardes the Fort, where hee preſently entred, finding it abandoned without any men at all, left for the defence thereof, hee went vp the Riuer ſide fiue or ſixe miles, where hee ſaw their Barnes and the ground where a great quantitie of Wheate had growne, which he carried with him to ſerue for Seed in <hi>Virginia,</hi> he ſaw likewiſe their Corne Mill very conueniently placed, which together with the Barnes hee left ſtanding vntou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched. As for the Fort it ſelfe he deſtroyed it downe to the ground, razing the <hi>French</hi> Armes, and leauing no monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment remayning, that might witneſſe their being there.</p>
            <p>After this <hi>Biencourt</hi> who had beene ſome where abroad trauelling through the Countrey, comming home deſired to conferre with Sir <hi>Samuell Argall,</hi> who did meete with him apart from the Company vpon a Medow, and after they had expoſtulated a ſpace for what had paſt contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerting concerning the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Engliſh</hi> Title to theſe bounds, at laſt <hi>Biencourt</hi> offered (If hee might haue a prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction) to depend vpon our King, and to draw the whole Furres of that Countrey to one Port, where he would di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide them with him, As likewiſe he would ſhew him good Metalls, whereof hee gaue him pieces, but the other refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ioyne in any ſocietie with him, proteſting that his Commiſſion was onely to diſplant him, and that if hee
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:180885:15"/>found him there, after that time hee would vſe him as an enemy. <hi>Biencourt</hi> labouring earneſtly to haue had the Ieſuit (as he confeſſed) with a purpoſe to hang him. Whilſt they were diſcourſing together, one of the Sauages came ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly forth from the Woods, and licentiated to come neere, did after his manner earneſtly mediate a peace, wondring why they that ſeemed to bee of one Countrey ſhould vſe others with ſuch hoſtilitie, and that with ſuch a forme of habit and geſture as made them both to laugh.</p>
            <p>After this <hi>Biencourt</hi> remoouing from thence to ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part, <hi>Monſieur Champlein</hi> who had liued long here, did carrie a company with him from <hi>France,</hi> of ſome fortie perſons or thereabouts vp the Riuer of <hi>Canada,</hi> whom hee planted on the North ſide thereof, with a purpoſe to ſerue for a Factorie, drawing all the Trade of that farre running Riuer (which a Plantation would haue diſperſed in many parts) within the hands of a few whom he doth command otherwiſe if his deſires had beene bended that way, hee might haue planted many people there ere now, the place is called <hi>Kebeck,</hi> where the <hi>French</hi> doe proſper well, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Corne by their owne labour, which may furniſh themſelues for food, and likewiſe for a ſtocke to traſſique with the Sauages, with ſundry Fruits, Roots, Vine, Grapes and Turkie Wheate. <hi>Champlein</hi> hath diſcouered the Riuer of <hi>Canada,</hi> from the Gulfe vpwards aboue twelue hundred miles, finding in it ſometimes ſuch falles, as to ſcape the ſame, he muſt carrie his Boate a little way by Land, and then hee did many times come to great Lakes at the end whereof hee did alwayes find a Riuer againe, and the laſt Lake where hee came was a very huge one, iudged to bee three hundred miles in length, by the report of ſome Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uages, who did affirme vnto him, that at the further end thereof they did find Salt-water, and that they had ſeene great Veſſels which made <hi>Champlein</hi> beleeue that a paſſage might be there to the Bay of <hi>California,</hi> or to ſome part of the South Sea, which would prooue an ineſtimable benefit for the Inhabitants of thoſe parts, opening a neere way to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:180885:16"/>
               <hi>China,</hi> which hath beene ſo many ſundry wayes with ſo great charges ſo long ſought for, howſoeuer in regard of the ſeaſon, and for want of neceſſary prouiſions, <hi>Champlein</hi> did returne backe at that time with a purpoſe to goe againe another yeere, which if he hath done is not yet knowne, but this is moſt certaine, that the Riuer of <hi>Canada</hi> hath a long courſe and through many goodly Countreyes, ſome of theſe great Lakes by ſending forth, or by receiuing great Riuers, do affoord meanes of commerce as farre as to ſome parts of <hi>Terra Florida,</hi> as may bee gathered by <hi>Champleins</hi> Diſcouerie. And now hauing giuen a breuiarie of all that is done by the <hi>French</hi> in <hi>America,</hi> will next report of that which hath beene done by ſome others.</p>
            <p>I will not here make mention of the many and braue Voyages that at the Sea haue happily beene performed by the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> which ſame by eternall records hath recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to be applauded by the beſt judgements of euery age, but I will only ſhortly touch that which they haue at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted by way of Plantation, beginning with the <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Land</hi> which was firſt diſcouered, and doth lie neereſt to this Countrey. Sir <hi>Humfrey Gilbert</hi> hauing a Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> did take poſſeſsion of it in her name at Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> Harbour, and thereafter purpoſed to haue ſeene <hi>Canada,</hi> but encountring with ſome vnexpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted croſſes as hee was returning from thence, ſeeking to condemne an opinion (malice or enuie ordinarily taxing all aſpiring ſpirits whoſe vertue by way of reflection doth vpbraide the baſeneſſe of others) that had beene conceiued of him as wanting courage, he precipitated himſelfe vpon an other extremitie, not to ſeeme fearefull, prouing deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate; for in the time of a ſtorme, out of a needleſſe braue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, to ſhew a contempt of danger, being in a little ſmall Pinnace, and refuſing to come to his beſt Shippe that was of a large burden, hee was ſuddenly ſwallowed vp by the waues neere to the Ile of <hi>Sablon,</hi> and his death did ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwe great hopes of a Plantation that by the generouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his minde might juſtly haue beene expected from
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:180885:16"/>him; but long before his time and euer ſince the <hi>Engliſh</hi> had vſed to fiſh vpon the Banke, and within the Bayes of <hi>Newfound Land,</hi> and the ſweetneſſe of the benefit arriſing from thence, did perſwade a companie compoſed of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doners</hi> and Weſt-country men to joyne together for ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſome to inhabite there, where before howſoeuer the Summer was large as hote as here, the Winter was thought vnſufferable.</p>
            <p>The firſt houſes for a habitation were built in <hi>Cupids</hi> Coue within the Bay of <hi>Conception,</hi> where people did dwell for ſundry yeeres together, and ſome well ſatisfied both for pleaſure, and profit, are dwelling there ſtill, finding ſmall difference betweene the ſeaſons of the yeere in that Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate, and here. There is another Plantation begunne at Harbour <hi>à Grace</hi> within the ſame Bay by the Citie of <hi>Briſtoll</hi> called <hi>Briſtols Hope,</hi> whereas by the ſowing and reaping of ſome Cornes of ſundry ſorts doth appeare what further may poſsibly be expected; And within theſe three yeeres Maſter Secretary <hi>Caluert</hi> hath planted a companie at <hi>Ferriland,</hi> who both for building and making triall of the ground haue done more then euer was performed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by any in ſo ſhort a time, hauing already there a brood of Horſes, Kowes, and other beaſtial, and by the induſtry of his people he is beginning to draw back yeerly ſome bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit from thence already: which courſe howſoeuer at firſt it proue good, or bad for his particular, is by example benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall for the publike.</p>
            <p>Laſt, I heare that my Lord Vicount <hi>Falkland</hi> now Lord Deputie of <hi>Ireland,</hi> hath this laſt yeere ſent a companie to inhabite at <hi>Renouze</hi> a place lying South-weſt from <hi>Ferri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> where the ſoyle is eſteemed to be the beſt whereupon any hath ſetled there as yet, and hee hath the ſhorteſt way, and beſt opportunitie of any within his Majeſties Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for tranſporting of people and cattell to that part from <hi>Ireland,</hi> which if his courſe bee rightly directed, as all haue reaſon to wiſh, may promiſe him a good ſucceſſe.</p>
            <p>The firſt Patentees for <hi>Newfound-land</hi> haue giuen mee
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:180885:17"/>a grant of that part thereof which doth lie North-weſt from the Bay of <hi>Placentia</hi> to the great Gulfe of <hi>Canada</hi> ouer-againſt <hi>New Scotland,</hi> where I had made a Plantation ere now, if I had not beene diuerted by my deſignes for <hi>New Scotland,</hi> but I purpoſe to doe it as ſoone as conueniently I may. The moſt part of the bounds whereupon any hath planted as yet in <hi>Newfound Land</hi> is found to be rockie and not fit to be manured: it may be theſe that made choice thereof (neglecting the Land) had onely a regard to dwell commodiouſly for making vſe of the Sea, the preſent pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits whereof doth recompence the loſſe of that which might be expected by the other, but there can be no hope of any conſtant dwelling where the people that inhabite doe not take a courſe to maintaine themſelues by their owne Cornes, and paſture, as all there might doe, if they would reſpect their poſteritie more then the preſent time.</p>
            <p>Before I come to the Continent I muſt remember the Iles of the <hi>Bermudas,</hi> whoſe Diſcouerie and Plantation was procured by ſo ſtrange a meanes, for a Ship happening to periſh vpon their Coaſt, her paſsingers ſeeking the next Land for a refuge, they were compelled to doe that out of neceſsitie whereunto in good reaſon, both for honour and profit, they might more warrantably haue beene inuited; Thus doth benefit flowe from loſſe, ſafety from ruine, and the Plantation of a Land from the deſolation of a Shippe: they found at the firſt ſtore of Hogs, which in all appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance had their beginning from ſome ſuch an accident as theirs was, and the Fowles were there in abundance ſo eaſie to be taken that they could ſcarcely be frighted away, theſe firſt people by repairing of their Ship which was caſt away vpon the Land, or by building ſome other Veſſell out of her mines, comming backe to <hi>England,</hi> and reporting what was paſt, ſome joyned together in a companie after they had taken a Patent thereof from the King, and did ſend people of purpoſe to inhabite there, who truſting too much to the goodneſſe of the ſoyle, and neglecting their owne induſtrie, or not gouerning that well which was car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:180885:17"/>with them, were reduced to a great diſtreſſe for want of victuals, ſo that, if they had not beene confined within an Iland (more ſenſible of a preſent ſuffering then capable of future hopes) they would willingly haue retired from thence, but a great quantitie of Ambergreece hauing been found by one by chance, and ſent backe in a Ship that was going for <hi>London,</hi> their Merchants finding it to bee of a great value, were ſo encouraged by ſuch a ſubſtantiall ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, that they preſently diſpatched away a new ſupply of perſons and all prouiſions neceſſary, who arriuing there, and hauing conſidered what a gulfe of famine was likely to haue ſwallowed their fellowes, they improuing their judgement by the others experience, by betaking them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to labour in time did preuent the like inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience; there is no Land where men can liue without la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, nor none ſo barren whence induſtrie cannot draw ſome benefit, All <hi>Adams</hi> poſteritie were appointed to worke for their food, and none muſt dreame of an abſolute caſe, which can no where ſubſiſt poſitiuely, but onely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratiuely, according to the occaſions more or leſſe.</p>
            <p>This Plantation of the <hi>Bermudas,</hi> a place not knowne when the King came to <hi>England,</hi> hath proſpered ſo in a ſhort time, that at this preſent, beſides their ordinary (and too extraordinarily valued) commoditie of Tobacco, they haue growing there Oranges, Figs, and all kind of fruits that they pleaſe to plant, and doe now intend to haue a Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar worke. Theſe Iles being about twentie miles in bredth can onely be entred into but by one paſſage, which is forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and eaſily commanded by Ordnance, ſo that, hauing no Sauages within, and fearing no forces without, it is eſteemed to be impregnable; and the number of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants there, being neere three thouſand perſons, are ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for the ground that they poſſeſſe, This part may proue exceedingly ſteadable to this State, if euer it happer to haue (as it hath heretofore had) any deſignes for ſeru<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e in theſe Seas.</p>
            <p>The firſt Plantation that euer the <hi>Engliſh</hi> intened a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:180885:18"/>was in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irginia,</hi> which was firſt diſcouered and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med ſo by Sir <hi>Walter Raleigh,</hi> who in the time of Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> did place ſome perſons, to inhabite there, who not being ſupplied in time, or out of ignorance, or lazi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, not vſing the ordinary means (the vſual fault of all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginners) were brought by famine to a great extremity. And Sir <hi>Francis Drakes</hi> comming by chance that way did tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port them backe with him to <hi>England,</hi> whileſt at the ſame time there was another companie furniſhed forth by Sir <hi>Walter Raleigh,</hi> who miſsing them whom they expelled to haue found there, did remaine ſtill themſelues; but what did become of them, if they did remoue to ſome other part, periſh, diſperſe, or incorporate with the Sauages (no monument of them remayning) is altogether vnknowne; This noble worke hauing ſo hard a beginning after a long diſcontinuance was reuiued againe in the Kings time by a companie compoſed of Noblemen, Gentlemen, and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, who (joyning priuate purſes with publike ſupplies) did ſend thither a ſufficient Colonie, well furniſhed with all things neceſſary, who after their firſt comming had a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall warre with the Natiues, till it was reconciled by a Marriage of their Kings ſiſter with one of the Colonie, who hauing come to <hi>England,</hi> as ſhee was returning backe, died, and was buried at <hi>Graueſend.</hi> Thus euen amongſt theſe Sauages (libertie being valued aboue life) as they were induced to conteſt in time, before that power which they ſuſpected, could come to ſuch a height, that it might haue a poſsibilitie of depreſsing them, ſo was their malice with their feares, quickly calmed by the meanes of a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage; Lawfull allyances thus by admitting equalitie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue contempt, and giue a promiſcuous otf-ſpring extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing the diſtinction of perſons, which if that People become Chriſtians, were in ſome ſort tolerable, for it is the onely courſe that vniting minds, free from jealouſies, can firſt make ſtrangers confide in a new friendſhip, which by communicating their bloud with mutuall aſſurance is left here<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ary to their poſteritie.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:180885:18"/>
            <p> This longed for peace, though it bred a great content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the time, was attended by wrapping them that apprehended no further danger (too common an inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient vp in the lazie remiſſeneſſe of improuident ſecuritie. For a number leaning the feate of the mayne Colonie, did diſperſe themſelues to liue apart, as if they had bin into a well inhabited Countrey, which (as perchance) it had em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boldened the Sauages to imbrace the firſt occaſion of a quarrell, ſo did it giue them an caſie way for executing the miſchiefe that they intended, by killing two or three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred perſons before they could aduertize one another, farre leſſe, ioyne to oppoſe them in a company together, which courſe might not onely then haue made them able to reſiſt, but preuenting the others reſolution had kept them from being purſued: yet I heare of late, that they haue reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged this iniury (though (as ſome report) not after a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable manner) by killing their King, with a great number of the chiefe of them whom they ſuſpected moſt.</p>
            <p>This Plantation of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irginia,</hi> if it had not beene croſſed by the Incurſion of the Sauages abroad, and by the diuiſion of their Owners at home, had at tayned to a great perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ere now, hauing had Inhabitants from hence to the number of neere three thouſand perſons, and if ſome of them who are there, being Lords of reaſonable proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of ground, and hauing people of their owne, owing no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but due obedience to a Superiour Power, and the lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of a life conforme to the Lawes, had no care but (ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king their Lands to maintayne themſelues) how to build, plant, and pleniſh in ſuch ſort as might beſt eſtabliſh a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune for their Poſteritie, they might quickly make vp a new Nation, but it is a great discouragement vnto them who dwell there, that they muſt labour like the Seruants of a Family, purchaſing their food and rayment from <hi>England,</hi> in exchange of Tobacco, as they are directed by their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, many whereof are ſtrangers to the eſtate of that bounds, and intending to ſettle none of their Race there,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:180885:19"/>haue no care but how the beſt benefit may preſently bee drawne backe from thence, the number of voyces at their aſſemblies preuayling more then the ſoundneſſe of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, otherwiſe that Countrey before this time for Wine, Oyle, Wheate, and other things neceſſary for the life of man might haue equalled for the like quantitie any bounds within <hi>Europe,</hi> to which the ſoile of it ſelfe lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king nothing but the like induſtry is no way inferiour. And it is to be exceedingly wiſhed by all his Maieſties ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects that the Plantation of <hi>Virginia</hi> may proſper well, which lying neereſt to the part from whence danger might come, may proue a Bulwarke for the ſafetie of all the reſt.</p>
            <p>That which is now called <hi>New England</hi> was firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended within the Patent of <hi>Virginia,</hi> being the North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſt part thereof, it was vndertaken in a Patent by a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Gentlemen in the Weſt of <hi>England,</hi> one of whom was Sir <hi>Iohn Popham</hi> then Lord Chiefe Iuſtice, who ſent the firſt company that went of purpoſe to inhabit there neer to <hi>Segadahoek,</hi> but thoſe that went thither, being preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to that enterprize, as endangered by the Law, or by their owne neceſſities (no enforced thing prouing pleaſant, diſcontented perſons ſuffering, while as they act can ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome haue good ſucceſſe, and neuer ſatisfaction) they after a Winter ſtay dreaming to themſelues of new hopes at home returned backe with the firſt occaſion, and to iuſtifie the ſuddenneſſe of their returne, they did coyne many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes, burdening the bounds where they had beene with all the aſperſions that poſſibly they could deuiſe, ſeeking by that meanes to diſcourage all others, whoſe prouident forwardnes importuning a good ſucceſſe, might make their baſe ſluggiſhneſſe for abandoning the beginning of a good worke, to be the more condemned.</p>
            <p>About a foure yeeres ſince, a ſhippe going for <hi>Virginia,</hi> comming by chance to harbour in the South-weſt part of <hi>New England,</hi> neere Cape <hi>Cod,</hi> the company whom ſhee carried for Plantation, being weary of the Sea, and enamo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the beautie of the bounds that firſt offered it ſelfe vnto them gorgeouſly garniſhed with all wherewith
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:180885:19"/>pregnant nature rauiſhing the ſight with variety) can grace a fertile field, did reſolue to ſtay, and ſeated themſelues in that place which is now called <hi>New Plimmouth,</hi> where they haue builded good houſes, and by their owne induſtry haue prouided themſelues in ſuch ſort as they are likely to ſubſiſt, keeping a good correſpondencie with the Captaines of the Sauages, who haue done nothing hitherto that might offend them (and after this) though they would dare at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt nothing to their preiudice, who are now aboue two hundred perſons, and doe increaſe their number yeerely. They find both the Land and the Seas there abounding in all things needfull for the vſe of man, and doe gouerne themſelues after a very ciuill and prouident manner.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Ferdinando Gorge</hi> hath beene a chiefe man for the furtherance of all things that might tend to the aduance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>New England,</hi> hauing beene at great charges theſe many yeeres paſt for the Diſcouerie thereof, in doing which (a good intention bent for other ends, caſually bringing forth this effect) the fiſhing there(not ſought for) was found, which doth prooue now ſo profitable, as fortie or fiftie Sayle are imployed there from <hi>England</hi> yeerely, and all that haue gone thither, haue made aduantagious Voyages.</p>
            <p>This laſt yeere, hee ſent his Sonne Captaine <hi>Robert Gorge</hi> with a Colonie to be planted in <hi>Meſſaſuats</hi> bonds, and as I heare out of a generous deſire by his example to encourage others for the aduancement of ſo braue an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprize he is reſolued ſhortly to goe him ſelfe in perſon, and to carrie with him a great number well fitted for ſuch a purpoſe, and many Noblemen in <hi>England,</hi> (whoſe names and proportions as they were marſhalled by lot, may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare vpon the Map) hauing interreſſed themſelues in that bounds, are to ſend ſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uerall Colonies, who may quickly make this to exceed all the other Plantations.</p>
            <p>Hauing ſundry times exactly weighed that which I haue alreadie deliuered, and beeing ſo exceedingly enflamed to doe ſome good in that kinde, that I would rather bewray
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:180885:20"/>the weakneſſe of my power, then conceale the greatneſſe of my deſire, being much encouraged hereunto by Sir <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinando Gorge,</hi> and ſome others of the vndertakers for <hi>New England,</hi> I ſhew them that my Countrimen would neuer aduenture in ſuch an Enterprize, vnleſſe it were as there was a <hi>New France,</hi> a <hi>New Spaine,</hi> and a <hi>New England,</hi> that they might likewiſe haue a <hi>New Scotland,</hi> and that for that effect they might haue bounds with a correſpondencie in proportion (as others had) with the Countrey whereof it ſhould beare the name, which they might hold of their owne Crowne, and where they might bee gouerned by their owne Lawes; they wiſely conſidering that either <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irginia,</hi> or <hi>New England,</hi> hath more bounds then all his Maieſties ſubiects are able to plant, and that this purpoſe of mine, by breeding a vertuous emulation amongſt vs, would tend much to the aduancement of ſo braue a worke, did yeeld to my deſire, deſigning the bounds for mee in that part, which had beene queſtioned by the <hi>French,</hi> and lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the limits thereof to bee appointed by his Maieſties pleaſure, which are expreſſed in the Pate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t granted vnto me, vnder his great Seale of his Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> marching vpon the Weſt towardes the Riuer of Saint <hi>Croix</hi> now <hi>Tweed</hi> (where the <hi>Frenchmen</hi> did deſigne their firſt Habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) with <hi>New England,</hi> and on all other parts it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed by the great Ocean, and the great Riuer of <hi>Canada,</hi> ſo that though ſundry other preceding Patentes are ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginarily limited by the degrees of the Heauen, I thinke that mine be the firſt National Patent that euer was cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bounded within <hi>America</hi> by particular limits vpon the Earth.</p>
            <p>As ſoone as my Patent was paſſed, reſoluing to take poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of the Lands, that were granted vnto me, I proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded my ſelfe of a ſhip at <hi>London,</hi> in the moneth of March, in <hi>Anno</hi> 1622. but that the buſineſſe might beginne from that Kingdome, which it doth concerne, whereby ſome of my Countrimen might be perſwaded to goe, and others by conceiuing a good opinion thereof, to depend by expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:180885:20"/>vpon the reports of ſuch of their acquaintance, as were to aduenture in that Voyage, I directed her to go about by <hi>S. Georges</hi> Channell, to <hi>Kirkcubright,</hi> where ſhe arriued in the end of May; Some Gentlemen of that country, vpon whoſe friendſhip I repoſed moſt, happening at that time to bee out of the Kingdome, I encountred with ſundry vnexpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted difficulties: the prizes of victuals beeing within the ſpace of three monethes, ſince I had parted before from <hi>Scotland,</hi> ſuddenly tripled, and yet ſo ſcarce as I could hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in haſte bee well furniſhed, yet ſince I was ſo far aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, leſt I ſhould looſe that which was done, if I did not the reſt, I vſed the beſt diligence I could to prouide the ſhippe with all things neceſſary. Then the very people ſpecially Artizens, of whom I ſtood in need, were at firſt loth to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barke for ſo remote a part, as they imagined this to bee, ſome ſcarce beleeuing that there could bee any ſuch bounds at all, and no wonder, ſince neuer any in that part had euer trauelled thither, and all nouelties beeing diſtruſted, or diſualued, few of good ſort would goe, and ordinarie perſons were not capeable of ſuch a purpoſe.</p>
            <p>At laſt, in the end of Iune, they parted from thence to the Ile of <hi>Man,</hi> and after ſome ſtay there, in the beginning of Auguſt, leauing the ſight of his Maieſties Dominions, did betake themſelues to the Sea. Though by reaſon ſo the lateneſſe of their ſetting forth, they had the windes very contrary about the middeſt of September, they diſcouered Saint <hi>Peters</hi> Ilands, and were neere to Cape <hi>Bretton,</hi> but yet were beaten backe againe by a great ſtorme to <hi>New-found-land.</hi> And as they paſſed by the Bay of <hi>Placentia,</hi> neglecting the occaſion to place themſelues in ſome part of my bounds, there as they might haue done, they went in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> Harbour, where they concluded to ſtay that Winter, and ſent the ſhip home for a new ſupply of ſuch things as were needfull.</p>
            <p>Though it might haue diſcouraged mee much, that they had retired to <hi>New-found-land,</hi> foreſeeing that what they had with them might be waſted, and that it would bee as
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:180885:21"/>chargeable and difficult to furniſh them forth from thence, as if they were to goe of new from <hi>Scotland,</hi> yet rather then they ſhould bee in danger for want of prouiſion, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king me any way guiltie of their loſſe, that had aduentu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red their liues, truſting to my care, I fraughted a ſhippe of purpoſe furniſhed with ſuch things as were required in a Note, which they ſent home with their Meſſenger. This ſhippe was diſpatched by mee from <hi>London</hi> in the end of March 1623. but ſhee happened to ſtay ſo long at <hi>Plimmouth,</hi> firſt, vpon ſome neceſſary occaſions, and laſt by contrary winds, it being the eight and twentieth of April, before ſhee parted from thence, hauing no good windes at all, that they arriued not at Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> Harbour, till the fift of Iune. At their comming they found the company not fit for a Plantion which had firſt by an vnexpected cauſe been deuided in two during the Winter, and in May ſome doubting of a ſupply, had engaged themſelues to ſerue Fiſhermen, by which meanes they gained their main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, and ſome meanes beſide, ſo that they could hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be gathered together againe, and their Miniſter and Smith (both for Spirituall and Temporall reſpects, the two moſt neceſſary members) were both dead, ſo that ſeeing no hope to plant themſelues in any good faſhion that yeere, ten of the principall perſons concluded to go alongſt with the ſhip to <hi>New Scotland,</hi> to diſcouer the Countrey, and to make choice of a fit place for a Habitation againſt the next yeere, conſidering very well, that they could not doe ſo much good by ſtaying there with ſo few a number, as they might doe at their returne, by reporting the truth to their friends, of that which they had ſeene, whereby a new Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonie might be encouraged to ſet forth well furniſhed, and inſtructed according to that which might bee learned by their experience.</p>
            <p>The three and twentieth of Iune, they looſed from Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> Harbour, and ſayled towards <hi>New Scotland,</hi> where for the ſpace of fourteene dayes, they were by fogges and contrary winds kept backe from ſpying Land till the eight of Iuly, that they ſaw the Weſt part of Cape <hi>Bretton,</hi> and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:180885:21"/>till the thirteenth day, they ſayled alongſt the Coaſt, till they ranne the length of Port <hi>de Mutton,</hi> where they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered three very pleaſant Harbours, and went aſhore in one of them, which after the ſhippes name, they called <hi>Lukes</hi> Bay, where they found a great way vp a very plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Riuer, being three fathom deep at a low water at the entry thereof, &amp; on euery ſide of the ſame they did ſee very delicate Medowes, hauing Roſes white and red, growing thereon wtih a kind of wilde Lilly, which had a daintie ſmel, the next day they reſolued (coaſting alongſt the land) to diſcouer the next Harbour, which was but two leagues diſtant from the other, where they found a more pleaſant Riuer then the firſt, being foure fathome deepe at a low water with Medowes on both ſides thereof, hauing Roſes and Lillies growing thereon as the other had, they found within this Riuer, a very fit place for a Plantation, both in regard that it was naturally apt to be fortified, and that all the ground betweene the two Riuers, was without wood, and very good fat Earth, hauing ſeuerall ſorts of beries growing thereon, as Gooſe-beries, Straw-beries, Hind-beries, Rasberies, and a kind of red Wine berie, as alſo ſome ſorts of graine, as Peaſe, ſome Eares of Wheate, Barly and Rie growing there wilde; the Peaſe grow in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance alongſt the Coaſt, very bigge and good to eate, but did taſte of the fitch, this Riuer is called Port <hi>Iolly,</hi> from whence they coaſted alongſt to Port <hi>Negro,</hi> beeing twelue leagues diſtant, where all the way as they ſayled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longſt, they ſpied a very pleaſant Countrey, hauing grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing euery where ſuch things as were obſerued in the two Harbours where they had beene before. They found like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in euery Riuer abundance of Lobſters, Cockles, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhel-fiſhes, and alſo not onely in the Riuers, but all the Coaſt alongſt, numbers of ſeuerall ſorts of Wild-foule, as Wild-gooſe, blacke Ducke, Woodcocke, Crane, Heron, Pidgeon, and many other ſorts of Fowle which they knew not. They did kill as they ſayled alongſt the Coaſt great ſtore of Cod, with ſeuerall other ſorts of great fiſhes.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:180885:22"/>The Countrie is full of Woods not very thicke, and the moſt part Oake, the reſt are Firre, Spruce, Birch, with ſome Sicamores, and Aſhes, and many other ſorts of Wood which they had not ſeene before. Hauing diſconered this part of the Countrie, in regard of the Voyage their ſhip was to make to the Straits with fiſhes, they reſolued to coaſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longſt from <hi>Lukes</hi> Bay to Port <hi>de Mutton,</hi> beeing foure leagues to the Eaſt thereof, where they encountred with a <hi>Frenchman,</hi> that in a very ſhort time had made a great Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, for though he had furniſhed one ſhip away with a great number of fiſhes, there were neere ſo many readie as to load himſelfe &amp; others. After they had taken a view of this Port, which to their iudgement they found no waies inferiour to the reſt they had ſeene before, they reſolued to retire backe to <hi>New-found-land,</hi> where their ſhip was to receiue her loa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of fiſhes. The 20. of Iuly they looſed from thence, and the ſeuen and twentieth thereof they arriued at Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> Harbour, and from thence ſailed alongſt to the Bay of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception,</hi> where they left the ſhip, and diſpatched themſelues home in ſeuerall ſhips that belonged to the Weſt part of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is no wonder, that the <hi>French</hi> beeing ſo ſlieghtly planted, did take no deeper roote in <hi>America,</hi> for they as onely deſirous to know the nature and qualitie of the ſoile, and of things that were likely to grow there, did neuer ſeeke to haue them in ſuch quantitie as was requiſite for their maintenance, affecting more by making a needleſſe oſtentation, that the World ſhould know they had beene there, then that they did continue ſtill to inhabit there, like them, that were more in loue with glorie then with vertue, then being alwaies ſubiect to diuiſions amongſt themſelues, it was impoſsible that they could ſubſiſt, which proceeded ſometime from emulation or enuie, and at other times from the lazineſſe of the diſpoſition of ſome, who (lothing labor) could bee commanded by none, who would impoſe more vpon them then was agreeable with the indifferencie of their affections and ſuperficiall endeuours.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:180885:22"/>
            <p> The <hi>Engliſh</hi> were free from theſe mutinies, and wanted not induſtry enough, but their out of a cuſtome they haue to trauell more for the benefit that doth flow from graſſe, then by manuring of the ground for Corne, or otherwiſe if they were forced ſo to doe by their Owners at <hi>London,</hi> who enforcing a ſpeedie returne by their labour, would needs be truſted with furniſhing of them victuals, they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying themſelues to Tobacco, and ſuch things as might import a preſent commoditie, neglecting the time that might haue beene imployed for building, planting and husbandrie, did liue but like hired Seruants, labouring for their Maſters, and not like Fathers prouiding for their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily and Poſteritie, which can neuer bee auoided till the ground be inhabited by them, that being Owners thereof, will truſt it with their maintenance, and doe content them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with the delight of that which may giue glorie to them, and profit to their heires.</p>
            <p>The Plantations in <hi>America</hi> doe approch neereſt to the puritie of theſe that (by an induſtrious diligence) in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancie of the firſt age did extend the mutiplying generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Mankind, to people the then Deſert Earth, for here they may poſſeſſe themſelues without diſpoſſeſsing of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, the Land either wanting Inhabitants, or hauing none that doe appropriate to themſelues any peculiar ground, but (in a ſtraggling company) runne like beaſts after beaſts, ſeeking no ſoile, but onely after their prey. And where of old the <hi>Danes, Gaules, Gothes, Hunnes, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>andals, Longo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bards,</hi> and thereafter <hi>Sarazens, Turkes,</hi> and <hi>Tartarians,</hi> did (with an inundation of people) encroach vpon theſe places of <hi>Europe,</hi> which were moſt ciuill, and where the Goſpel was beſt planted, out of an ambitious enuie to draw vnto themſelues the glory that any Nation had formerly gained, or out of an exorbitant auarice to ſwallow vp their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and to vſurpe (if they had power challenging right) any Lands that were better then their own, as the moſt part did in <hi>Greece, Hungary, Spaine, Italy</hi> and <hi>France.</hi> Wee here goe to cauſe preach the Goſpel where it was neuer heard,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:180885:23"/>and not to ſubdue but to ciuillize the Sauag ruine could giue to vs neither glory nor benefit, ſince in place of fame it would breed infamie, and would defraud vs of many able bodies, that hereafter (beſides the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an dutie in ſauing their ſoules) by themſelues or by their Poſteritie may ſerue to many good vſes, when by our meanes they ſhall learne lawfull Trades, and induſtries, the Authors whereof (though preuenting the like Superſtition) may acquire no leſſe reuerence from them, nor in like caſe of old <hi>Saturne, Bacchus, Ceres</hi> and <hi>Pallas,</hi> by teaching to plant Corne, Wine, and Oyle, did get from the credulous ignorance of them with whom they communicated their knowledge.</p>
            <p>When I doe conſider with myſelfe what things are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie for a Plantation, I cannot but be confident that my owne Countreymen are as fit for ſuch a purpoſe as any men in the world, hauing daring mindes that vpon any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable appearances doe deſpiſe danger, and bodies able to indure as much as the height of their minds can vndertake, naturally louing to make vſe of their owne ground, and not truſting to traffique. Then <hi>Scotland</hi> by reaſon of her populouſneſſe being conſtrained to disburden her ſelfe (like the painfull Bees) did euery yeere ſend forth ſwarmes whereof great numbers did haunt <hi>Pole</hi> with the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme kinde of drudgeric (if not dying vnder the burden) ſcraping a few crummes together, till now of late that they were compelled, abandoning their ordinary calling, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take themſelues to the warres againſt the <hi>Ruſſians, Turks,</hi> or <hi>Swedens,</hi> as the <hi>Polonians</hi> were pleaſed to employ the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, others of the better ſort being bred in <hi>France,</hi> in regard of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient league, did finde the meanes to force out ſome ſmall fortunes there, till of late that the <hi>French</hi> though not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether violating, yet not valuing (as heretofore) that friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip which was ſo religiouſly obſerued by their predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours, and with ſo much danger and loſſe deſerued by ours, haue altered the eſtate of the Guards, and doe derogate fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our former liberties, which this King now raigning, we
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:180885:23"/>hope, will reſtore to the firſt integritie. The neceſsities of <hi>Ireland</hi> are neere ſupplied, and that great current which did tranſport ſo many of our people is worne drie. The <hi>Lowe Countries</hi> haue ſpent many of our men, but haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched few, and (though raiſing their flight with ſuch bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed feathers, till they were checked by a preſent danger) did too much vilipend theſe fauourable Springs by which their weakneſſe was chiefly refreſhed: But howſoeuer ſome particular men might proſper vnder a forraine Prince, all that aduenture ſo, doe either periſh by the way, or if they attaine vnto any fortune, doe loſe the ſame by ſome colour that ſtrict lawes vrged againſt a ſtanger can eaſily affoord, or elſe naturalizing themſelues where they are, they muſt diſclaime their King and Countrey, to which by time (the obiect of their affections altered) being bound to haue a care of that part where there poſteritie muſt liue, they turne euery way ſtrangers, which neceſsitie impoſed vpon them to take this courſe, and inconuencies following thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, may be preuented by this new Plantation. And where the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Merchants before had no trade but by tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Commodities that might haue beene imployed at home, and oftentimes monie, to bring backe Wine from <hi>France,</hi> and Pitch, Tarre, and Timber from the Eaſter Seas. Now only by exporting of men, Corne, and Cattle, they may within a little time be able to furniſh back in exchange theſe things before named. As likewiſe a great benefit of fiſhes, Furres, Timber and Metals, drawing forth our peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to forreine Traffique, wherewith they neuer haue bin accuſtomed before, and that to the great increaſe of the Cuſtomes, helping hereby to enrich that ancient King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, which of all the reſt hath onely loſt by his Maieſties greatneſſe, being hereby not onely defrauded of his owne preſence, and of the comfort that his countenance did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually affoord, but likewiſe of many Commodities ariſing to any Countrie where a Court is Reſident, as the vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall pouertie thereof (hauing few rich vnleſſe it bee ſome
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:180885:24"/>Iudges and their Clerkes) by a common complaint doth too ſenſibly teſtifie.</p>
            <p>I haue neuer remembred any thing with more admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on then <hi>America,</hi> conſidering how it hath pleaſed the Lord to locke it vp ſo long amidſt the depths, concealing it from the curioſitie of the Ancients, that it might be diſcouered in a fit time for their poſteritie, they were ſo farre of old from apprehending it by any reach of reaſon, that the moſt lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men (as they thought) by infallible grounds, in regard of the degrees of the Heauen, did hold that theſe Zones could not be inhabited, which now are knowne to include the moſt pleaſant parts in the Word. This neuer came to the knowledge of any Hebrew, Greeke, or Roman, who had the moſt able mindes to haue found out ſuch a myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: and howſoeuer ſome would gloſe vpon that Fable of <hi>Platoes</hi> Atlantick Iland, I haue neuer obſerued any thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Ancient Writers tending to ſuch a purpoſe, if it be not theſe lines of <hi>Seneca</hi> the Tragedian, whereby hee might (if not with a prophetick, yet with a poetick rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) deliuer that which he had a mind to make the poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie expect, and was in poſſibilitie to happen.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enient annis—</l>
               <l>Secula ſeris, quibus occanus</l>
               <l>Vincula rerum laxet, &amp; ingens</l>
               <l>Pateat tellus, Tiphiſque nouos</l>
               <l>Detegat orbes; nec fit terris</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltima Thule.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And it is a thing not yet comprehended by the courſe of naturall reaſon, how theſe parts of the World came firſt to be peopled: We muſt grant (according to the grounds of Diuinitie) their people to be deſcended from <hi>Noah,</hi> and it is not long ſince that (the Loadſtone being found out) the beſt Saylers (ſcorning as in former times to be only coaſters) haue brought the Art of Nauigation to that perfection, that they durſt reſolutely aduenture to ſearch the moſt remote
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:180885:24"/>parts in the Ocean, and if any had gone thither of purpoſe to inhabite, they would haue carried with them the moſt vſe full kindes of tame Cattle, ſuch as Horſes, Cowes, and Sheepe, whereof neuer any was found in theſe parts, till they were tranſported thither of late yeeres; but onely ſuch wild beaſts as of themſelues might haue wandred any where through vaſt Forreſts, and Deſerts: ſo that I doe thinke there muſt bee ſome narrow paſſage vpon the Eaſt, towards <hi>Terra Auſtralis Incognita,</hi> not yet diſcouered, from whence people by time might haue come (croſſing the Straits of <hi>Magelane</hi>) to inhabite <hi>Braſile, Chile,</hi> and <hi>Peru,</hi> or rather I ſhould thinke that there were ſome Continent, or Narrow Sea towardes the North, about the Straits of <hi>Anien,</hi> from whence the firſt Inhabitants in <hi>America</hi> might haue come; becauſe the wild beaſts that are there are creatures moſt peculiar to the North, ſuch as Elkes, Beares, and Beauers, which are knowne to bee ordinary with the <hi>Ruſſians,</hi> and <hi>Tartarians;</hi> and I am the more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed in this opinion, when I remember of the Mountains of Ice that come floting euery Spring alongſt the Coaſt of <hi>New-found-Land,</hi> which (as it is likely) may diſſolue from ſome Sea that hath beene frozen during the Winter time, ouer which people, and wild beaſts might haue commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to paſſe; but this is a matter that can hardly bee deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined by demonſtration or reaſon, therefore (all men for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming that which they know not, according to the ſquare of their owne conceits.) Wee muſt leaue this to the vnli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited libertie of the imagination of man.</p>
            <p>But the thing moſt wonderfull of all is this, though now it bee cleerely diſcouered, that ſo few are willing to make vſe therof; This doth chiefly proceed from want of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, few being willing to aduenture vpon that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they are not acquainted by their owne experience, and yet thoſe who haue not made triall themſelues, if they will truſt others, may bee abundantly ſatisfied by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports of a number, who to Plant and Traffique doe yeerely
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:180885:25"/>haunt theſe parts. If the true eſtate of that which might bee done at this time by the ioyning of ſome reaſonable company together were rightly vnderſtood, then ſo many would not liue at home as they do, loſing their time, where they can make no benefit, and burdenable to them to whom they are not vſefull, rather admitted, then welcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, the one thinking that their ſeruice ſhould deſerue a reward, and the other that their maintenance is an vnne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary charge, neither gaining, and both diſcontented: then would not ſo many aduenture their liues for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of ſtrangers, whereby they ſcarce can acquire that which doth defray their owne charges, and howſoeuer the hope of Honour may flatter a generous ſpirit, there is no great appearance by this meanes to prouide for a Family, or for a Poſteritie. And if we rightly conſider the benefit that may ariſe by this enterpriſe abroad, it is not onely able to afford a ſufficient meanes for their maintenance, who can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not conueniently liue at home, by disburdening the Countrey of them, but it is able to enable them to deſerue of their Countrey, by bringing vnto it both Honour and Profit.</p>
            <p>Where was euer Ambition baited with greater hopes then here, or where euer had Vertue ſo large a field to reape the fruites of Glory, ſince any man, who doth goe thither of good qualitie, able at firſt to tranſport a hundred perſons with him furniſhed with things neceſſary, ſhall haue as much Bounds as may ſerue for a great Man, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon hee may build a Towne of his owne, giuing it what forme or name hee will, and being the firſt Founder of a new eſtate, which a pleaſing induſtry may quickly bring <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o a perfection, may leaue a faire inheritance to his poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, who ſhall claime vnto him as the Author of their Nobilitie there, rather then to any of his Anceſtours that had preceded him, though neuer ſo nobly borne elſwhere, and if the vaſteneſſe of their hopes cannot bee bounded within their firſt limits, as ſoone as they haue ſtrengthned
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:180885:25"/>themſelues for ſuch a deſigne, either by Sea or by Land, (in regard of the large Countries next adiacent hereunto) there doth alwaies reſt a faire poſſibilitie of a further encreaſe, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for them, or for their ſucceſſours; and ſo euery one of inferiour ſort may expect proportionably according to his aduenture: The Merchans that are giuen to trade, where can they haue a fairer ground for gaine then here; and that beſides that which may bee expected from ſo fertile a Land by induſtry or husbandry hereafter, in preſent commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, ſuch as Cod fiſhes and Herring in the Seas, Salmonds in the Riuers, Furres, Pype-ſtaues, Pot-aſhes, and all that may ariſe from the plentie of good Wood, Mineralls, and other things though not knowne to ſtrangers that onely coaſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longſt the Lands, that may bee diſcouered hereafter by them that are to inhabite the Bounds.</p>
            <p>Here thoſe that are ſo diſpoſed, without making a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſticall retreate (free from a multitude of troubles) may inioy the pleaſures of contemplation, being ſolitary when they will, and yet accompanied when they pleaſe, and that not with ſuch company as (preſſed by importunitie) they muſt diſcontentedly admit, but onely by them of whom they haue made choice, and whom they haue carried with them, with whom (as partners of their trauells) by mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall diſcourſes they may remember their former dangers, and communicate their preſent ioyes: heere are all ſorts of obiects to ſatisfie the varietie of deſires. I might ſpeake of the ſport that may bee had by Hunting, H<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wking, Fiſhing, and Fowling, where all theſe creatures haue had ſo long a time for increaſe, without being deſtroyed or frighted, as likewiſe of the great contentment that muſt come by daily diſcoueries of new Fieldes and Riuers, with the diuerſitie of things not ſeene before that may happen to bee found in them: but I would rather haue all at firſt to thinke of the paines they muſt indure, in bringing of ſo notable a Worke to perfection, ſince no good thing can be had with eaſe, and all the ſonnes of men are borne to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour.
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:180885:26"/>But leauing theſe worldly reſpects, the greateſt incouragement of all for any true Chriſtian is this, that heere is a large way for aduancing the Goſpel of Ieſus Chriſt, to whom Churches may bee builded in places where his Name was neuer knowne; and if the Saints of Heauen reioyce at the conuerſion of a Sinner, what exceeding ioy would it bee to them to ſee many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of Sauage people (who doe now liue like brute beaſts) conue<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ted vnto God, and I wiſh (leauing theſe dreames of Honour and Profit, which doe intoxicate the braines, and impoyſon the minde with tranſitory pleaſures) that this might bee our chiefe end to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin a new life, ſeruing God more ſincerely then before, to whom we may draw more neere, by retyring our ſelues fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from hence.</p>
            <p>As I would haue no man that hath a mind for this courſe, to abuſe his iudgement, by truſting too much to the ferti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of the bounds where he is to goe, and too little to his owne prouidence, and induſtrie, whereby he may be made to neglect the preparing himmſelfe for this Voyage after ſuch a manner as is requiſite, So I altogether diſl<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke them that poſſeſſed with the prepoſterous apprehenſions of feare (like the lazie man of whome <hi>Salomon</hi> ſpeaketh, that pretending difficulties to preuent trauell, would ſay there was a Lion in the way) will needs imagine the worſt that is in poſſibilitie to happen: for ſuch a man (too inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niouſly ſubtill in coniecturing danger) doth both by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudicated opinions diſable himſelfe, and diſcourage them, who not being duely informed, are confirmed by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence of other vndertakers, that profeſſe to haue know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, there is no man at home where he was borne, ſo free from the accidents of fortune who may not quickly by a publike, or by a priuate calamitie be brought in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to ſuffer, and much rather ſhould wee arme our ſelues with a high reſolution againſt all inconuencies that can occurre in ſuch a forraine enterpriſe (being circumſpectly
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:180885:26"/>prouident, but not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>founded with a deiecting feare) where the greatneſſe of ſo well grounded hopes for vs and for our Poſteritie ſhould make vs (hoping for pleaſure) to diſgeſt any preſent paine, with a courage greater then can bee bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by any apprehended trouble. And becauſe the Lord in ſuch eminent Exploits doth commonly glorifie himſelfe by a few number, I wiſh that all ſuch whoſe hearts doe miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue them portending any diſaſter (like them of <hi>Gideons</hi> troupes that bowed downe like beaſts to the water) ſhould retire in time, ere the contagiouſneſſe of their infirmitie come to infect them that are more ſoundly diſpoſed. There is no iuſt cauſe for a reaſonable man to feare any worldly thing, but onely diſgrace and want of neceſſary maynte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance: A man can hardly fall in the firſt here, ſince an honourable intention what euer the ſucceſſe prooue muſt acquire prayſe, and the other by ordinary meanes, is eaſie to be auoyded, but I am ſo farre from painting out a ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed facilitie to ſnare weake minds, that I would haue none (with whom it is not fit to communicate more then they be capeable of) to imbarke in this buſines, but only ſuch as do reſolue againſt the worſt, for I profeſſe as <hi>Cato</hi> did, when he was to enter the Deſerts of <hi>Arabia.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>—Neque enim mihi fallere quenquam</l>
               <l>Eſt animus, tectoque metu perducere vulgus.</l>
               <l>Hi mihi ſint comites, quos ipſa pericula ducent,</l>
               <l>Qui me teste, pati, vel quae tristiſſima, pulchrum,</l>
               <l>Romanumque putant; at qui ſponſore ſalutis</l>
               <l>Miles eget, capiturque animae dulcedine, vadat</l>
               <l>Ad Dominum meliore via.—</l>
            </q>
            <p>And laſt ſhould not theſe memorable Exploits of late performed in the Eaſt and Weſt <hi>Indies</hi> by the <hi>Flemmings,</hi> enflame vs with a generous ardour to equall, or rather to exceede them, whoſe penuritie of people (euen at home) muſt bee ſupplyed by the ſuperfluitie of ours: They haue
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:180885:27"/>not onely in the Eaſt <hi>Indies</hi> by ſeuerall Habitations appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priated large Territories to themſelues, but likewiſe to the great preiudice of their Neighbours, improouing their owne profit, haue engroſſed the generall Commerce by conſequence depending thereupon. And if they ſeate themſelues (as it is likely they will doe) in <hi>Braſill,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidently proſecuting the good beginning that they haue gotten by ſparing people of their owne, or by intere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Strangers whom they dare truſt for founding of a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient Colonie, that being ſtrong enough to defend and command the Inhabitants. (Securely exacting a due obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience) may enable them for greater matters; then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fining with the very Springs whence the ſtreames flow that entertayne the power of their enemies (exhauſting their ſubſtance both by Sea and Land) they haue a maruellous faire occaſion offered to aduance themſelues by depreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the oppoſed partie whoſe proſperous and deſired ſucceſſe (whileſt the adding to one doth derogate from another) if not emulated in time, will bee enuied here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
            <p>I know that many of my Nation if they had beene as willing as they are able had beene more fit then I am for this purpoſe, but yet it hath oftentimes pleaſed God to doe the greateſt matters by the meaneſt Inſtruments. And as no one man could accompliſh ſuch a Worke by his owne priuate fortunes, ſo if it ſhall pleaſe his Maieſtie (as he hath euer beene diſpoſed for the furthering of all good Works more for the benefit of his Subiects, then for his owne par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular) to giue his helpe accuſtomed for matters of leſſe moment hereunto, making it appeare to be a Worke of his own, that others of his ſubiects may be induced to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>curre in ſuch a common cauſe, no man could haue had my charge that with more affection and ſinceritie ſhould haue vſed his endeuours for diſcharging of the ſame, but I muſt truſt to be ſupplyed by ſome publike helps, ſuch as hath beene had in other parts, for the like cauſe whereunto, as I doubt not, but
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:180885:27"/>many will be willing out of the nobleneſſe of their diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for the aduancing of ſo worthy a Worke, So I hope will ſome others, the rather out of their priuate reſpect to me, who ſhall continue as I haue heretofore done, both to doe and write in ſo farre, as ſo meane an abilitie as mine may reach, what (I conceiue) may proue for the credit or benefit of my Nation, to whom I wiſh all hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
